all right hi everyone this is pleasure
of doubt and we're here with another
voices with ver Vicky's follow-up Q&A
session so today's guest is Taylor
Baggett of authentic relating Toronto so
he is a he has been the circling
facilitator for John rebecky
so he he's probably had a very
influential we know from him waking from
the meeting crisis what an impact
circulate has had on John's thoughts and
I'm I'm guessing Taylor's been a big
part of that and so he is very kindly
agreed to be with us today
and so again he's with authentic
relating Toronto and maybe we can start
off by asking so so what is authentic
relating and what is authentic relating
Toronto hmm yeah thanks first thing I
want to mention and I give John a bit of
grief for this because he had misspelled
my name so it's Taylor Barrett ours
instead of geez
oh no problem for a while and it if you
don't refresh the the link it it's those
you old spelling will blame John for
that but I will I'll make sure to to fix
the on ours as well yeah I've been
getting grief from from people in the
community like oh that's got to change
so yeah so I'm authentic relating
there's sort of two pieces to authentic
relating there's authentic relating as
sort of a to put it simply like a way of
being and then there's authentic
relating practice which is like a series
of exercises that sort of help us with
that way of being and imagine guy might
guys hang stock might argue this a bit
I'm which is fine considering he's
considered the founder of circling but
I'd say it's largely considered as
circling is an authentic relating
practice so for us when we talk about
authentic relating or what we talk about
or what we mean when we talk about
authenticity
is what we're striving for with our
authenticity z' that our outward
expression i'm more accurately reflects
our inner experience that's really what
we're sort of getting at is you know
another way of looking at looking at
that as maybe transparency so something
about that doesn't quite fit so it's
really like how much are we able to were
willing to put into words to express
what we're experiencing when we're in
relationship with somebody else whether
that's a business relationship a
friendship romantic relationship so
that's sort of the authentic relating
goal you know if we can even just you
know get 1% more authenticity in our
communication that's a little bit more
truth in that communication we're sort
of engaged in an authentic relating
practice I think it really in Toronto is
a community that was started probably
about nine nine almost ten years ago Co
started with was somebody who's still
involved Josh Stein and I forget the
name of the other guy right now and then
about five years ago my wife and I took
over leading the community from Josh as
he wanted to step away from it and were
you know I'm meet up we're a community
of Honor about nineteen hundred people
but in reality you know within a given
year we're probably seeing a couple
hundred unique people come through a lot
of people stick with it a lot of people
it's not for them or they're not ready
for it we have doing a little over a
hundred events a year right now related
to authentic relating practice
encircling we do trainings in offender
relating practice circling facilitation
self leadership so that's sort of what's
what's happening with this integrating
Toronto so are these online events or
in-person things well up until the
pandemic almost everything was in person
with the exception that we had just
recently started an online
version of our court practice series
which is you know where a group of a
handful of people are together for a
corridor doing weekly circling practice
that was the first online event that we
had that was consistent since the
pandemic we've moved everything online
but have had to cancel some of the
trainings just because the amount of
work to convert them online based on you
know just this was one gonna line up and
the people who want to do it really want
to do it in person so I've been sort of
in a holding pattern with some of our
more advanced things as a result of the
pandemic right so I'd like you to in a
minute
talk about circling maybe explain for us
what it is but so you said circling is a
part of authentic relating do you do is
circling the main part of your your
business so to speak or do you do do you
do events and activities outside of
circling yeah we definitely do things
outside is circling much like the the
experiment the project and dialectic
that Joan and I were talking about
currently running that under authentic
relating Toronto although I'm not sure
if it will stay there that I haven't
decided but it's been really good to use
people that have these circling
capacities into this just new type of
conversation but in terms of circling an
authentic leading practice yeah I would
say that's circling like one way to look
at is circling as sort of the marathon
it's sort of the main event and to me
authentic relating practice is going to
the gym and working the muscles so that
you can do the the marathon the the
framing I usually hold for authentic
relating practices it's you know you go
to a gym to sort of work on your
physical fitness to me authentic
relating is going into a gym to work
your emotional interior self awareness
muscles so we'll do a particular
experiment it has various constraints
like a piece of equipment in a gym would
and sometimes some of the gym equipment
feels really weird and contrived and
like really restrictive but you know it
you do the motion and you keep
you get stronger in that area so that's
sort of the frame that we've been
holding for a long time and then when
you've got you know this great physical
or emotional fitness then I think what's
available encircling is is almost
limitless so that's one frame I would
hold for it
so so so are there other but what other
activities other than circling would one
do in these in these sessions yeah so
the type of events that we have that
aren't circling specific we run events
called tea groups which is sort a short
for training groups which comes from the
sensitivity training groups from the
1950s and 60s so that's been around for
a while to the highly present moment
based exercise and you know the
intention of that exercise is to sort of
start to notice the impact that we have
on others through being stubbornly
committed to the present moment so
that's one type of practice that we've
been doing for a while we're one of the
few authentic relating communities in
the world that seem to be consistently
doing T group and I think it's a really
great sort of feather in the cap you
know to use John's phrasing a great
practice for an ecology of practices
that would help you say better at
circling and then we learn things called
connection labs which I would say is
just general authentic relating practice
where we do sort of a series of small
exercises you can call them experiments
in sort of relating we might do that in
pairs you might do it in triads as a
whole group but we usually do an evening
of that and run through you know a
half-dozen different exercises
sometimes around a theme you know maybe
the themes depth maybe the themes
sexuality maybe the themes awkwardness
and we just sort of orient the exercises
around people having those experiences
in relationship with one another and
recently back in December I started
making workshops which is not something
that we offered before and I managed to
create two new workshops one and as an
introduction to shadow work and I was
going to I started working on the next
one and then the pandemic sort of was
coming online and I decided to do an
actual proper introduction to authentic
relating Toronto that we've never really
had you know people sort of come in they
might come in from circling because they
heard about circling or they might come
in through connection lab and then
they'll never attend circling it's it's
actually kind of interesting how that
happens and some people just don't
really understand like they'll all get
emails like how do I become a
facilitator like I don't really want to
do this work and I guess whatever we
have on our websites just not clear
enough so I wanted to sort of really
clarify our message and what our
intention is and what's available so
that's still in process but we're
getting a lot clearer about what we're
up to so my last question before I open
it up so so John talked quite a bit
about circling in in awaking me from the
meaning crisis but he he doesn't go into
that much detail some people here may
have more or less an awareness of what
certainly is but could you just take us
through what what is circling
I said is that the end of our hour yeah
yeah yeah when we do an intro a night
and we introduce people due to the
practice it generally takes an hour
before a ready to actually start doing
the practice I'll take I'll take a
little stab at it that hopefully doesn't
take too long I'll keep it a bit generic
so the type of circling that we we tend
to offer in our drop-in events is what's
called birthday circling it's a
facilitated practice and somebody sort
of volunteers to have the group's
attention and we keep bringing our
attention like they become the focus of
our attention and what we're attempting
to do is
you sort of get and so much as we can
get what it's like to be them right here
right now with us and we do that by
asking them what it's like to be with us
and we share the impact of what it's
like for us to be with them so we sort
of start to notice what's here
between us in the present moment another
way to put it is it's an inter
subjective meditative practice meaning
we're generally talking about our
subjective first-person experience from
the interior and it's a meditation
because we're noticing what's happening
in us during the circle we're getting
information about what's happening for
the circle we and the others in the
circle and we also start to notice the
space between us or the the we space or
the collective space so that's the
meditative part of it that's about the
best I can do in a couple minutes
great well thank you very much so let's
open it up to two questions who has a
question for Taylor
don't be shy just just throw them out
there Taylor I was wondering about
circling in general you know what what
is the end goal like what things do you
think circling helps with alright that's
sort of an I mean it's a great question
and then the question makes perfect
sense one thing I want to sort of say
about is when I talk about circling I've
sort of gotten this feedback and it's
not specific to me I've heard other
people say it about other circling
leaders is that we sound sort of vague
and there's like this suspicion from
some people not everybody that like
we're like hiding something and I could
talk a bit though sort of why we do that
in a way and but it sort of depends on
what frame were sort of holding about
about sort of how we experience things
and how we experience reality and things
like that but what I would say is that
the the most simple answer I can give I
think for circling about what I'm
wanting for people in the practice is
freedom and what I mean by that is sort
of like the day of choice that they
notice their subjective patterns and
start to create choice to move it more
into the objective so I would say that's
sort of the thing that I wish for
everybody and that I think that the
practice is really good at doing like a
lot of people will do circling because
they get reflections back like a mirror
about what we call the water you're
swimming in sort of highlighting the
blind spots of our way of being and how
we're impacting people which is why I
think T group is a great associative
practice to circling but what we're
doing in the moment is we're just trying
to me more fully here and present so you
know there's that I don't know who
that's saying I think it's attributed to
allow so
but I don't I don't know if it's
actually his there's that saying that if
you're if you're worried you're living
in the past or sorry know if you're yeah
if you're depressed you're living in the
past if you're anxious you're living in
the future but if you're at peace you're
in the present moment and you know early
on after I I found circling after my my
wife or my then-girlfriend sort of had
showed or introduced me to this I I read
a book called a guide to the present
moment no particularly popular author
but what I really just sort of got from
that is there's that idea of the pursuit
of happiness and some argument about
whether or not that's a that's a good
pursuit something that you should
actually pursue but what I noticed is
through reading that book and sort of
mapping it out to my experience as a
circling in the early days of it was
that it seems like happiness like in its
purest form is only available in the
present moment so I think circling is is
a way to help us get really present
really aware of what's here between any
sized group of people to really get to
the deepest truth of the moment and
there's just something extremely freeing
and for a lot of people although it's
not our general orientation to sort of
steer people toward it in this way but a
very spiritual experience for a lot of
people so yeah there's a sort of quality
of experience that can be had in
circling and I think that's why a lot of
people continue to do it there's sort of
that introspection learning about
themselves and then there's that
different way of being with other people
that they didn't really know was
possible
hey Taylor thanks for doing this I have
a theory that almost everyone with a
name similar to Tyler turns out to be a
pretty swell person can you confirm or
deny this well considering that I was
referred to as Tyler for most of my
childhood yeah totally
fantastic so when I think one of the
easiest ways to alleviate the potential
fears that any new practice may brush up
against is to outline some of the
negative effects that we may have seen
unfold from them are there any serious
complaints that people may have had once
they've gone through the process or any
noticeable negative effects that that
that you've seen yourself I like that
question yeah appreciate that I think
what do I want to say about that the
interesting thing about circling is that
no two circles are the same and in fact
if we were say circling you and we did
it today and let's say we did it with
this group of people that are here
listening and then say two hours from
now or tomorrow I don't know we notice
I'm sent out again circle is gonna be
completely different what happens and
it's gonna be complete like they're like
snowflakes and some of the reason for
that is well primarily is because we're
different in every moment there's always
something else that's sort of happening
for us like when we do it again you'll
have the experience of the first one
carried over into this one and it will
shift how you experience it and I think
that's part of the reason why we try not
to really assert too much about what
people are gonna get out of circling so
for example you know encircling we will
do often a short meditation to sort of
connect to ourselves and the default of
that meditation is usually to sort of
focus on you know on our breath and just
sort of notice the breath moving through
the body they're very basic sort of
breath meditation but the thing is is
that this meditation isn't comfortable
for everybody and things can come up
even just in the meditation we're not
even into the circling practice yet so I
think there's something about circling
the sort of review
a uniqueness or things that make us
unique and in that we can all have very
very different experiences being circled
and some people who are maybe if we need
to label them I like a bit more avoid
and the process of circling can be
really confronting even though we have
agreements in the first agreement just
honor yourself and you don't have to do
or say anything you don't want to and
yet we don't all fully possess or stand
within that that power and autonomy so
to varying degrees in a circle we might
sort of give our power away to other
people in the circle to the facilitator
like we're just all so different and the
outcome of circling can be also
different so if I would say there's
anything that's like a consistent
outcome that I would label or
potentially label as negative is some
people realizing they're not ready like
they're not ready to really look at
what's already there
and I would say that's that that can be
reasonably consistent in terms of the
people who don't don't come back and
it's not even so much that the the
circle itself or the energies any way
hostile or anything like that it's just
you know we're inviting people into
vulnerability and some of us are more
used to it than others and some of us
are okay with a vulnerability hangover
and some of us are like oh my god they
almost think I'm an idiot
and they just don't come back anymore
but I would still say that's like I
think that's a fairly rare sort of thing
that happens and you know some circles
are just boring I'm like they can
actually just be boring right why isn't
what's that what's that
sorry I haven't microphone troubles here
no no I was just just agreeing with you
yeah but there's a wide range that can
go back and forth of me interaction
right yeah yeah exactly so I mean some
of them can even be boring and you know
for for those who you know come in
attached to a certain outcome and they
don't have that expectation that you
know they might not come back I think
that's pretty common for most practices
like you know we get out of the practice
will we put into it and if we're not
really really ready for the practice
then we're probably not gonna come back
to it period so I don't know that
circlings unique in any particular way
other than you know there's this
socialized sort of way in which we can
be where people are threatening people
can be really exciting but they can also
be really threatening and if we have
some like a real fear of judgment and
maybe not a lot of resiliency in that
area you know we might freeze up or or
just realize like oh yeah no I can't
that was way too scary I mean well I
definitely a different person same
content could be shared and they're just
like oh yeah like why don't we start
taking our clothes off you know this is
a really wide spectrum of what people
are looking for in relationship with
people in the practice and the cool
thing about it is the practice is very
flexible and that's also in some ways a
detriment because I can't actually tell
you what's going to happen in the circle
you may not want to actually reveal much
about yourself and we'll actually spend
most of the time in the circle in the
resistance of not wanting to share like
that's the thing we'll be with so we'll
actually necessarily learn not that
wherever there for content we know but
we're not necessarily gonna like you're
not going to be necessarily vulnerable
about the thing that you're resisting
being vulnerable about but maybe if we
can like more fully be with the
resistance that can that can be
interesting it can also be again this
sometimes can be boring yeah just
Tomica yeah and it really sounds like it
may depend on the skill of the
facilitator or whoever is helping to
shape that process it it seems like
there there is a great deal of variance
there with regards to how people will
respond to it as they come into it for
the first time
totally yeah totally I mean and that's
why we have a training course a
certification process you know there's a
number of groups out there that call
what they're doing circling and I would
necessarily call what they're doing
circling so you know that's sort of like
a it's the word like a result of the way
in which it was not her had not been
regulated you know had been no attempt
to sort of regulate it and you know it
was a very I know if you're familiar
with integral theory but it's you know a
very sort of green seeming process even
though I think it's an integral practice
it's a very green seeming process you
know like I think it attracts people who
were more in a green mindset and from
that place it you know there starts to
be things but now you should be like
sort of free for everybody you know like
let's you know let's not regulate it and
like we're sort of blind to the things
that happen when somebody turns around
and does bad therapy or something and
calls it circling like it it's it
potentially devalues the thing that the
people who know what they're doing are
doing or an offering so it's this sort
of a tricky thing when you have like a
generis Peschel II such a generic term
like the word circling right right
that seemed destined like a serious
branding issue and well how do you solve
that that's that is an interesting
question because then the authenticity
of it is in like the the procedure
itself right like in the and the acting
out of it yeah definitely definitely and
I think the way we've tried to address
is just to take more responsibility for
how circling showing up in the world
based on what we're bringing forward I'm
sorry
noticing all the beeps and I was
wondering how I could stop those so
that's sort of the approach that we've
taken and sort of expanding our training
deepening our training having different
prerequisites for people ready to ready
to start to practice with the general
public we have a certification process
so that's sort of we feel like the best
that we can do and as we continue to
sort of grow as leaders and teachers you
know that the training gets better it
gets sharper and yeah I mean that's I
feel like that's the best that we can do
in terms of what circling is and just
continue to to do what we're doing and
trusting it like really trusting the
process you know sharing it with other
people listening to feedback getting
feedback listening to the feedback that
other circling leaders or communities
are getting and I'm just sort of
navigating that way I like that strategy
it's sort of like being so bright that
any inauthentic competitor seems dull by
comparison yeah and you know I feel a
little bit protective of anybody who's
you know whose hearts in the right place
but maybe hasn't you know hasn't gotten
a really good training or has
prioritized a certain aspect of circling
over something else like you know one of
the things about circling that's maybe a
little bit different than a lot of
modalities is the facilitator at least
in the style of circling we do the
facilitator is also a participant so the
facilitators actually in a relationship
with the circle II so that means when
I'm facilitating like I'm bringing
myself forward what that means is that
if I'm haven't done my work you know if
I if I have particular maybe
developmental trauma or something's
happening in the circle that I'm I'm
subject to or reactive to I'm probably
bringing that into a relationship as a
facilitator so
that's the thing you know it's it's led
to us creating ethics documents and
everything else so that we're really
doing this practice in a responsible way
because we're inviting people into
vulnerability we're inviting people to
explore and ask themselves questions
that a lot of us don't tend to ask and
they can be really revealing and it can
be really confronting that can also be
amazingly healing and therapeutic as
well you know so that's a lot of the
reason why why we do the exploration but
we also have to be conscious that you
know not everybody is ready and
sometimes things are going to come up
and you might have a facilitator it
doesn't have much experience in the
practice isn't even aware of trauma
sensitivity you know and you can have an
interesting situation on your hands with
less experienced people who maybe didn't
learn circling from the school maybe
just watched a few videos online and
thought like I hadn't got the gist of
this and you know that's fine you know
if you're like hanging out with your
friends or whatever but you know when
you're creating an event and you're
putting it under a name and you've got
this structure trying to build a
community trying to to grow awareness of
a practice yeah I want to be really
careful like I just don't want anybody
to be hurt and I don't want that in any
practice but you know this is one that
I'm actually teaching this is one that
I'm actually facilitating so I'm really
taking trying to take responsibility for
what it is that I'm putting it there for
such potent work yeah well you know
maybe we could say more on that hurt
part because like as you were rightly
pointing out before there I'm sure
there's a lot of discomfort there's a
there's a lot of yeah and it's got to be
a lot of discomfort in the revealing and
the unveiling of of these things that we
try to run from so often so I think it
maybe is it's almost the the
confrontation of these these dark parts
of ourselves seem almost inevitable as
an aspect of this deep authentic
relation process for at least for most
of us so I think yeah I don't know I
feel like the the presentation of the
whole thing if it's conversant with with
like the full experience it acknowledges
that there is some aspect of this which
which may prick a little or may may
bruise or at least begin massaging a
bruise that's long been hurting perhaps
yeah yeah definitely yeah I think that's
sort of the nature of the exploring you
know like I think so many what is it
Stan takun says 99 he's a relational
psychotherapist there's a lot of
relationship work I'm he wrote a book
called he's written a few books actually
around relationships in love and now he
says 99 or 98 percent of everything that
we do is automatic like we're just
reactive beings there's not a lot of
conscious thought throughout our day so
we're just reacting to things that are
integrated into our body system and you
know as we grow up and develop certain
we want to call them contractions you
know can get formed through the growing
up and through the developmental process
and these sort of become maybe to use a
nice term like a sticking point for us
in relationship you know usually it's
somewhere where as a child you were sort
of told your way of being is not okay
you know your expression is not okay
you're too much or you're not enough or
whatever that is you know and it gets
really integrated and and then as we
sort of grow up and move into you know
adulthood and we move into that that
real busyness that real 99% of our day
being automatic and sort of engrained
and like a real habit and pattern it can
be confronting just to sit in a circle
in silence and slow down like just to
sort of like okay you don't have to do
anything right now we're just you just
need to be in so much if you can allow
yourself to be in this moment in just
that by itself like just that slowing
down can bring up things like you know
the awareness of a stress that's there
that we've we've pushed back or pushed
aside because we had a job to do or the
kids needed to get to school or I need
to make dinner or I've got papers due or
whatever that is you know whatever the
business of our life distracts us from
from what's already here so even just
that you know opening part of a circle
for sometimes I've been in I've been in
some circles but we sit down we come out
of the meditation and immediately the
circle he's crying and like that you
know they they weren't doing that five
minutes ago so something in the slowing
down something in the witnessing or
being witnessed um in that place just
that name itself can open things up for
people and that opening can be a real
release can be a real amazing experience
to sort of just feel like you're being
accepted as you are in the moment and
you don't have to do anything in that
and itself can be such a beautiful thing
for some people and for others it can be
super confronting because you know their
third day today is managing and trying
to keep it together and you know when
you're in the circle and you don't have
to do anything you don't have to really
care take anybody you don't we don't
really have a destination other than to
be more fully here with each other yeah
those things open up yeah which is
amazing and cool and it's just not a way
that a lot of us are it's not a place
that we visit frequently if at all so
once we do once we start to do that yeah
it can be confronting for sure yeah well
said thank you thank for that I'll step
back and let someone else take over yeah
no thanks for the questions Tyler it's
great
anyone else have any questions yeah go
ahead go ahead
aye Taylor thanks for sharing today I'm
curious you it sounded like you
mentioned that you have run groups that
have been like a consistent week to week
same set of people as opposed to groups
where you know it's just kind of random
each each time what what have you
noticed in those groups where there has
been that consistency yeah yeah no for
sure yeah so what we've noticed is and
what consistently happens is the way
that I would phrase it is we start to
get I start to feel a little more safer
and I sort of you can't see me because
this is in that video but I put quotes
around the word safer because number one
when we're in the group or no we're
gonna see the other people in the group
next week so when it comes to sort of
revealing something or like sharing
something that might be really edgy like
to turn around and tell somebody like
I'm really annoyed that you said that
like that can be really hard for
somebody to say especially if they're a
conflict avoidant um however you know
based on the agreements that we sort of
hold in the space and the knowing that
that person is committed to being there
again I've seen it allow more
possibility and what people will share
because of this safety and this trust
either trust based on how the other
people in being in the group have been
responding to them or interfacing with
them or trust in that like I know at
least I'm going to see you next week and
even though there's only five minutes
left in our call like we can clean this
up next week so those sorts of things
really seem to free us up to to sort of
start to have these maybe riskier
expression
and from that place we are more able to
go deeper into sort of our experiences
or our truth in the in the group in the
relationship so that's a very consistent
thing that we see in that group which is
why we you know run the group a little
bit smaller too so it's a little bit
more intimate when we run the circles in
those groups whereas you know if we do a
drop-in event we might have you know ten
people in a circle or as when we're
doing the core practice group we you
know we only have about five or six
people in each circle and the other
piece too is like you can you can carry
on a thread or you can start to notice
patterns and sort of like oh what is it
about this guy I'm always like getting
butt up with with you know with Tom over
here we always seem to be sort of like
avoiding each other you know like it
takes repeated sort of time in these
relationships to start to notice these
things unless you're like have a really
good and high capacity of self-awareness
and perception so so yeah it's just more
like more is available in the committed
groups beyond the fact that we're
actually doing you know over a quarter
you know 40 hours or so circling over
that span of time compared to a drop-in
event where we might do just under two
hours of it there's that more obviously
some more practice but we can just sort
of deep and what's already there because
we've had all these past experiences and
I'm seeing a similar thing also happened
in the experiment that I'm running to -
John and I were talking about the the
recent branch of it that I I started
with with Josh Stein we're doing a
series of three sessions about two and a
half hours of peace and what we're
noticing is in these you know collective
intelligence campfires that were calling
them in these conversations
more is available there's less filtering
as we go into the subsequent sessions so
more seems to be available in the space
there's more energy there's more what I
would call lifeforce and that's I just
think that's you know that's sort of the
ingredient that we're really looking for
that that makes these practices so
exciting things that people have
reported that have helped them you know
that after circling like what sort of
improvements they see yeah well I mean
yeah I would say they they run the the
gamut but I know one thing that I've
noticed is you know there's some people
that sort of have a bit more of a
punitive part of themselves and people
being able to sort of manage or be more
a choice about that or to feel an easing
of that voice about critical voice in
themselves I've definitely heard a lot
of reflections of that improving for
them like it being lasts or being more
manageable so that's certainly one one
example that I can think of certainly
with the experience of feeling accepted
as you are you know what we say when we
do circling as we say circling is not
therapy like we're not here to change
you we're not actually here to like heal
you like if you have a pro league it's
not a support group and you know an
underlying theory on I'm sort of
accepting somebody as they are can be
seen in Gestalt therapies the
paradoxical theory of change and that
one sort of suggests that the more in
which we try to get somebody to change
the more they dig their heels in and
it's only when we can come to acceptance
of them that they can start to accept
themselves and the real transformations
possible and we've seen that we've seen
that a lot I mean
just for me has been massive and my own
development the anecdote that I usually
share about circling is before I came
into it I felt very misanthropic like I
really didn't like people and I sort of
blamed everybody out there for
everything that was wrong in my life
something that I inherited I lovingly
from my father but nonetheless embodied
quite wholeheartedly and sort of through
the practice of circling and being with
other people and you know we see how how
alike and also how different we are it's
a beautiful way of getting a different
perspective
I remember having some experiences with
people of different races and sort of
hearing that firsthand accounted being
with them I get the way in which were
with somebody encircling about an
experience that I I can't have as a
middle-aged white guy but I can really
feel and be with and get a real taste
through through the practice of what it
was like for those people to go through
some of the experiences that they've
shared encircling and I can imagine
although I can't confirm but I can
imagine feeling heard and seen in that
place by somebody who normally can't
relate to that is it's got to be well
calling it special is probably
undercutting it a fair bit so so yeah I
mean even even just some people starting
to bring more self awareness in being
able to notice distinctions and their
emotions you know like rather than just
being mad it's like I know it's some
frustrated actually no no it's more of a
quality of an annoyance um actually no
it's more like I'm flustered like even
just adding on to an emotional
vocabulary and sort of self awareness of
what somebody's feeling and being able
to notice that in the moment and then do
that translation into articulating it in
real-time is huge for having deep
grounded immediate conversation so
I mean that's a handful of things but I
mean people are transformation like
actual transformation is possible with
encircling I've seen it all the time and
it's happened to me as well so yeah I
mean we could we could laundry list all
the things that are possible but there's
there's a handful anyways anyone else
have a question they want to throw out
okay are there any online resources for
circling and you've seen I knew you
would recommend I suppose it depends on
what we're talking about when we when we
say resources if it's like things to
read about the practice I would say I
don't nothing I can't think of anything
that's necessarily wrong with what's out
there
however given it's such a highly
experimental or experiential practice I
think just reading one you know
authentic relating organizations
perspective on circling is a bit
limiting so I aim that I actually sort
of encourage you like you can check out
guys hang stocks circling Institute
there's some online platforms that are
doing circling although I I struggle to
to recommend some of them based on some
things that I've heard there is a
platform that's circling Europe runs
called circle anywhere and where they
run daily circles I they do a different
flavors circling called
well they do birthday circling as well
but they also have another version sort
of called surrendered leadership that I
would say is an amazingly potent
practice but it's not not accessible to
everybody it's sort of my judgment about
it I've defended the practice a lot I
love those guys the three guys that lead
that that group in that practice I
recently spent a week with them back in
January doing one of their advanced
trainings just to sort of see like
what's happening with them I've got
nothing but the the highest respect for
what they're doing and I think if you
attended one of our circling events and
then attended one of their circling
events you would see like a huge
difference
and sort of the way in which the
practice is held and I don't want to say
one's better or worse I would just say
that I think ours is a little bit more
sustainable it's a little more sorry I'm
not sustainable accessible ours a little
more accessible and there's mm-hmm is a
little I'll say edgier I'm for lack of a
better term much more confronting I
would say and that's that really lends
to the potency of that practice - so who
was the more confronting group I would
say I would say Circle in Europe I would
say surrendered leadership practice is
is substantially more confronting and I
you know my hesitation to like
wholeheartedly recommended is you know
it's like there's like so many
conditions I think it could be perfect
I love the practice personally myself
however there are some people that I've
had in you know circles at art that I
would I would never recommend that they
go into a surround with leadership space
so yeah it's it's sort of like a next we
can call it a next-level practice and
some people sort of argued like should
we really call this circling and to a
degree they've sort of kind of pulled
back from calling the surrendered
leadership side of what they're doing
circling and then they added birthday
circling sort of a style of circling
that we do it or drop in events and
they've added those and I imagine those
are much more accessible I imagine they
hold them a little bit differently for
us at art we for drop-in events we have
a Yein first approach and if you're
familiar with the young longing sort of
like more of a feminine compassion
versus a masculine compassion default
and we sort of go go more to to the
inside for our drop-in events with
surrender leadership well I mean it just
sort of depends on who's the one that's
leading but I don't think they they
don't really have a policy it's it's
more like what the facilitation or the
group is sensing in the moment and
that's sort of what they go
and I've had moments where I've sort of
taken on a like dropping the frame that
I hold for birthday circling in our
circles and I've had some people sort of
in you know on the outside sort of like
whoa what was that
you know like they just sort of like not
what they were expecting and it was
great and like it's just you know great
experience in the circle but we've we've
tried to create something that's a
little bit more consistent that I think
fits better for a public open to the
newcomers sort of situation and we tend
to only go into the more edgy side of
circling and truth-telling
in our advanced training courses one
question I'd like to ask you
so John talks a lot about the religion
that's not a religion are you familiar
with that yes so I tell me if you
haven't given this a lot of thought but
I'm sure you have I I think John sees
circling as part of that how you know
we're just at the beginning stages of
just conceiving what this religion
that's not a religion can even look like
but have you thought about how circling
could be a part of that and what it
might look like yeah I mean the best way
I know how to sort of explain it or why
or to sort of justify why I think that's
correct
is I would go to developmental theory
and you know I'm I know a decent amount
of about integral theory and you know
Ken Wilber his most recent book was the
religion of tomorrow where he sort of
posits what you know what the next sort
of thing that would emerge that's a
religion and everything that I've heard
John say and and Jordan Hall around this
really largely he sort of maps on to a
lot of what Ken Wilber was saying I'm
sure there's some important distinctions
but like as a general frame
work they're sort of talking about the
same thing they're just using a
different like orientation or a
different basis you know John coming
more from cognitive science and and can
be coming more from you know just his
experience of the world sort of wisdom
and the great religions so why not when
I think of circling I a sort of a claim
that circling is an integral practice
and what I mean by that is I think that
circling can meet people at whatever
developmental level that they're at as
like a participant meaning it's a very
dynamic practice meaning that if you
have a really good sort of awareness of
human development that you can really
talk to people using this modality using
this sort of way of engaging way of
being with people in a way in which they
can feel I've seen accepted heard learn
things about themselves you know and
they don't have to be quite so developed
so for me I see like circling in sort of
I wouldn't even say a stripped down at
all I would just say I could see
circling you know be brought into
schools and to change the way in which
children at a very fundamental level
start to communicate with one another
you know there would be certain things
that I probably wouldn't necessarily do
if I was facilitating a circle of
children because you know I'd be trying
to use the practice to meet them at the
developmental level you know I'm not
going to go into you know I'm sort of
spiritual practice or like the hyper
sensitivity that I can have in the
moment you know that feels like I'm on
psychedelics because I'm so in the here
and now I think I'm not gonna go into
that with you know with a kid but for
them to like really start sharing like
really transparently really
authentically like hey how did how did
that make you feel you know when when
Chris turned away like that you know
like to really just call forward you
know that truth and
and to accept you know everybody whether
they're children or not you know where
they're at like I just like I think so
many of the problems or the difficulties
that we see in in our world in society
really stem from developmental trauma in
mom way or another and I believe that
authentic relieving practice which
includes circling brought into to
schools like at the earliest stages
you know like with that consciousness of
sort of not trying to change somebody
but to really appreciate them as they
are in this moment is so immensely
powerful that you know I think that the
whole world would transform and there
are some people trying to do that trying
to bring authentic relating into schools
there is a group that's been bringing it
into prisons and has had some fantastic
success there see I just you know
because of the level that I see this
practice working at being higher than
where we are socially like as like as a
civilization it's like a higher level
than where we are as a whole it's a
practice that can help pull us through
to the next sort of stage of development
as a society and you know I think that's
in many ways a lot of the things that
that Jordan and and John are sort of
talking about it's it's a you know this
finding of a new meaning like looking
for meaning within but acting in service
is something that's greater than
yourself I mean in many ways that's the
basis of so many religions no matter how
they sort of twist and twist the the
messaging you know that's sort of the
individual felt sense which John
obviously goes into the specifics of a
lot of the great religions in his series
but yeah I just I just see I just see
this type of practice this sort of
present moment focused truth-telling
you know a lot of yen a lot of holding
with a little bit of challenge is exist
exactly what all of us need and needed
you know when we were growing up and for
various reasons you know our her parents
and our society you know had its own
challenges that it was dealing with and
it wasn't really able to do the best job
so I think this practice and practices
like this are are just critical for
Humanity's sustainability oh what a
great what a great note to end on I
think that 705 I want to thank you so
much Taylor for coming here and
answering answering questions I think I
think we got a lot out of it I know a
lot of people here are very interested
in in this practice and and looking
forward to learning more apologies for
that name from at the beginning I
haven't had your name spelt right
everywhere except in my initial notes
that I took off the first video and that
happened to be one yeah at that minute
apologize for that but but thank you
again you're welcome to come back
anytime we would love to to have you
dancer dancer question to just talk
about talk about these things or even
even demonstrate circling if that's
something you you'd like to do here on
the forum and and of course you're
welcome to take part in our forum and in
this community that's that's been
developing yeah thanks thanks Brett
appreciate the invite it's exciting to
see sort of as I've been scrolling
through the the engagement what John's
doing like I think he's such an
important piece of the puzzle and I'm
also really grateful to to John's
interest in circling and and the support
that he's also given me and what we're
doing and so yeah just any anything to
sort of help promote or move along or
spread the word of this work
you know of us really looking in on
what's most important and what's really
meaningful for us and ways in which we
can sort of bring that into into our
lives in a more conscious way I'm sort
of getting away from all the automatic
behavior yeah it's anything that's in
service of that I'm just really happy to
be to be a part of so thanks for what
you're doing and and the invite and for
everybody is sort of engaging in these
questions and in these this thought
process in this sense making like we
these these are the things that we need
we need more of it yeah thank you
all right so thanks everyone for joining
us for this Q&A we will end the
recording now we'll be putting it up on
the awakening from the meaning crisis
discord YouTube channel and the links
are up in the up in the I think I forget
what it is there's links above put it in
the announcements for the YouTube for
the YouTube channel and I think each
other for recording and have a great day
everyone